A Guide to the Walter A. Jacobs papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA169
Rockefeller Archive Center
Walter A. Jacobs papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1906-1980, bulk 1914-1957
1914-1957
Rockefeller Archive Center
Jacobs, Walter A. (Walter Abraham), 1883-1967
FA169
3.96 Cubic Feet 9 boxes
9 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Walter Abraham Jacobs. 1883-1967. Chemist.
Jacobs was born in New York, New York on December 24, one of five children of Charles and Elizabeth (Friedlander) Jacobs. He earned his A. B. from Columbia College in 1904 and completed his A. M. one year later. Jacobs then attended Berlin University where he worked with Emil Fischer, receiving his PhD. in 1907. He joined the staff of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research as a fellow that same year.
Jacobs started as an assistant to P.A.T. Levene (1908), working on the chemistry of nucleic acids. In his own division of chemotherapy (later changed to chemical pharmacology), he worked on correlating chemical structures with bactericidal action. In 1911, Jacobs was promoted from assistant to associate. A year later, he was promoted to associate member of the RIMR. Work with Michael Heidelberger, Wade H. Brown, and Louise Pearce resulted in the development of tryparsamide which was clinically used in the treatment of African sleeping sickness and neurosyphilis. In recognition of this work, he was made an Officer of the Order of Leopold II by the Belgian government (1953) and was promoted to Member in 1923. He then started work on the isolation, characterization, and determination of the structure and synthesis of a large class of closely related natural products, beginning with the study of drugs useful in the treatment of heart disease. Jacobs studied digitalis, saponins, ergot alkaloids, aconite and veratrine alkaloids, and with Lyman Craig, the isolation of lysergic acid. In 1949, he retired and held the position of member emeritus until his laboratory was closed in 1959.
Jacobs was a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (Fellow), American Chemical Society, American Society of Biological Chemistry, Harvey Society, National Academy of Sciences, Sigma Xi, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, and the Society for Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics. On October 7, 1908, Jacobs married Laura F. Dreyfoos. They had two children, Walter C. and Elizabeth R.
Jacobs moved to Los Angeles, California in 1962, where he died on July 12, 1967.
He was awarded the Officer of the Order of Leopold II, Belgium 1953.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 6 series.
Further arranged primarily in alphabetical and in chronological order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 J156
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical material, correspondence, notebooks, notes, writings, and photographs.
Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical sciences; Cardiology; African trypanosomiasis; Medical research; Medical education; DNA; Pharmacology; Tryparsamide; Biology -- Research; Chemistry; Biochemistry; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Levene, P. A. T. (Phoebus Aaron)
- Biographical Material, 1942-1980; 1; 1 folder
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes biographies (RU and NAS); clippings; correspondence; and recollections of Walter's life by Laura F. Jacobs (wife) with notes by Michael Heidelberger.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Biographical Material, 1942-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1916-1957; 2; 1.76 Cubic Feet
  Includes correspondence, memos, notes, papers, reports, and reprints.
  Correspondents include Detlev W. Bronk, Lyman C. Craig, Louis F. Fiesar, Waldo R. Flinn, Journal of the American Chemical Society, Journal of Organic Chemistry, Otto Krayer, Arthur B. Lamb, Karl Paul Link, Randolph T. Major, Merck and Company, National Academy of Sciences, Nobel Prize Committee, Office of Scientific Research and Development, S. William Pelletier, Paul Rathgeb,? Raymond-Hamet, Tadeus Reichstein, Thomas Rivers, Yoshio Sato, Edric B. Smith, Edward S. Stein, Florence M. Stewart, David Todd, Douglas Whitaker, and K. Wiesner.
  Subjects include Jacobs' annual reports.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondents' last name, then arranged in chronological order.
  - A-D, 1941-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - F, 1932-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - G-JBC, 1916-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - JOG-JZ, 1937-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - K, 1936-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - L, 1921-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - M-MEM, 1930-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - MER-MZ, 1926-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - N-NAS, 1948-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NAS, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NAS, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NAT-NZ, 1940-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - O, 1943-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - P-PEL, 1931-1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - PEL-PZ, 1942-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - R-RAZ, 1929-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - RE-REP, 1937-1957 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - REPORTS, ANNUAL, 1933-1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    [See also: (7) 8]
  - REPORTS, ANNUAL, 1941-1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - REPR-RIN, 1937-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - RIV-RZ, 1937-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - S-SM, 1933-1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - SO-SZ, 1937-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - T, 1925-1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - U-V, 1941-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - W-Z, 1937-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1916-1936; 3; 0.88 Cubic Feet
  Includes bound books of notes.
  Researchers include Bertrand, Collins, Elderfield, Gustus, Michael Heidelberger, Hoffman, Walter A. Jacobs, Post, and Wignall.
  Subjects include tryparsamide.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by names on notebooks, then arranged in chronological order.
  - Bertrand, Collins, Elderfield, 1923-1936 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gustus, Hoffman, 1925-1928 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Heidelberger, 1916-1921 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Jacobs, 1914-1919 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Jacobs, (Tryparsamide), 1919-1929 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Jacobs, 1921-1926 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Jacobs, 1926-1930 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Jacobs, 1930-1933 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Post, Wignall, 1924-1933 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Laboratory Notes, 1931-1955, undated; 4; 0.2 Cubic Feet
  Includes correspondence, notes, and papers.
  Subjects include aconite alkaloids, digitalis, quatain, sapogenin, sontoquine, and strophanthidin.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Laboratory Notes - Aconite Alkaloids, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Laboratory Notes - Sapogenin, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Laboratory Notes - Sontoquine, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Laboratory Notes - Strophanthidin, Digitalis, Quatain, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1906-1960, undated; 5; 0.2 Cubic Feet
  Includes articles, bibliographies, correspondence, and reports.
  Subjects include Jacobs' annual reports and P.A.T. Levene
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Bibliography, 1906-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Levene, P.A.T. (re), 1941-1943 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Reports of Scientific Work, 1916-1943, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    [See also: (3) 5-6]
- Photographs, 1908-1956, undated; 6; 0.88 Cubic Feet Extemt is approximate.
  Includes glass slides, negatives, and personal photographs.
  Subjects include Walter A. Jacobs and P.A.T. Levene.
  - Photographs - Personal, 1908-1956, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Negatives (Box 8)
  - Glass Slides (Box 9)